Guide to the Vardan Hovhannisyan video collection AD.MC.001
AbuDhabi
Vardan Hovhannisyan video collection
1988-1994
AD.MC.001
AbuDhabi
128.0 Video recordings 128 video recordings (30:16 hours)
Collection consists of film footage that has been copied in digital format as mp.4 files. The original formats from which the copies were made include 8 mm, Beta, Beta SP, and VHS. The collection is divided into 128 segments of varying lengths, with a total running time of 30 hours, 16 minutes.
The Vardan Hovhannisyan video collection consists of films recorded or collected by cameraman and documentary filmmaker Vardan Hovhannisyan, primarily in Armenia and the surrounding Caucasus region, during the years leading up to and following the dissolution of the Soviet Union. The collection comprises 128 separate film clips, documenting protests in Yerevan against the Soviet government in the waning days of the Gorbachev government, demands for independence for Armenia, protests against the Soviet reaction to the conflict in the region of Nagorno-Karabakh, memorial marches and ceremonies for victims of fighting in Nagorno-Karabakh, footage of Armenian fighters in combat with Azerbaijani forces in Nagorno-Karabakh, and footage of the aftermath of the Spitak earthquake of 1988, in northern Armenia. Also includes footage of protests and similar events in Ukraine and Latvia.
Hovhannisyan, Vardan, Mr
Biography
Vardan Hovhannisyan is an Armenian filmmaker who founded the Bars Media Documentary Film Studio in Yerevan, Armenia in 1993. Between 1988 and 1991, he worked as a camera man, working on assignment for various news agencies, recording events related to the conflict in the contested region of Nagorno-Karabakh, as well as events leading to the collapse of the Soviet Union and the independence of Armenia.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection may only be accessed onsite, at the New York University Abu Dhabi Library, on dedicated computer work stations.
Existence and Location of Originals
The original footage from which these copies were made is held by the creator, Vardan Hovhannisyan, and his company, Bars Media Documentary Film Studio, in Yerevan, Armenia (http://www.barsmedia.am/).
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was reproduced, and copies were transferred to New York University, by Vardan Hovhannisyan, in 2014.
Arrangement
The film footage is arranged in one series of mp.4 files, in the order in which they were received from the filmmaker. The films are numbered both by specific identifier numbers assigned for use in the NYU digital repository, and also by a sequential number (from 1 to 128) for use in this finding aid.
Scope and Contents
The Vardan Hovhannisyan video collection consists of films recorded or acquired by cameraman and documentary filmmaker Vardan Hovhannisyan in Armenia and the surrounding Caucasus region, during the years leading up to and following the dissolution of the Soviet Union. The collection is not arranged in any distinct series, but contents can be loosely grouped into the following chronological and topical segments (with running time in hours and minutes for each group, and listing of numbered segments included in each category):
Protests against the Soviet authorities (circa 1988-1990): Most of this footage depicts protests in Yerevan, including rallies held in Opera Square, at which dissidents and nationalist leaders spoke, including future Armenian president Levon Ter-Petrosyan, then leader of the Pan-Armenian National Movement. Much of this footage includes speakers decrying the response of the Soviet authorities to the violence in the region of Nagorno-Karabakh, persecution against Armenians in other parts of the Azerbaijan S.S.R., calls for unification of Nagorno-Karabakh with an independent Armenian republic, as well as calls for greater political liberalization, human rights, and protests against environmental pollution. Time: 10:27:29 Segments: 1-2, 5-12, 15-21, 24, 29-30, 34, 37-38, 44-51
Protests in other parts of the Soviet Union (circa 1988-1990): These include movements in Latvia and Ukraine, including coverage of a congress of representatives from various Soviet republics in Kiev, protests against the aftermath of the Chernobyl nuclear disaster, and the aftermath of clashes in Riga, Latvia, between pro-Soviet forces and supporters of Latvian indepdendence in 1990. Time: 2:43:16 Segments: 22-23, 48, 52
Clashes between Armenian militia and Soviet forces, 27 May 1990: These segments document the aftermath of fighting between Armenian militia and forces of the Red Army, which broke out at Sovetashen (now Nubarashen), a suburb of Yerevan, and including footage of damage to a railway station, and footage of Soviet military forces moving through the city and sporadic fighting throughout the day, as well as funeral processions for Armenian fighters killed that day. Time: 1:55:35 Segments: 39-43
Nagorno-Karabakh—early fighting (circa 1988-1990): coverage of funerals of those killed in the fighting, footage of villages and civilians in affected areas, skirmishes, evaculations of civilians, as well as evacuations of Armenians from other areas of Azerbaijan after persecution. Time: 2:13:52 Segments: 13-14, 25-28, 31-33, 35-36
Spitak earthquake of December 1988, and its aftermath: Footage of the immediate aftermath of the earthquake, the arrival of search and rescue teams from the United States and Western Europe, excavation of bodies from rubble of buildings, damage in Gyumri (Leninakan) and surrounding areas, as well as condolences sent from officials and church leaders in October 1989 to those who suffered from the Loma Prieta earthquake in Northern California. Time: 1:56:39 Segments: 3-4, 73-79
Nagorno-Karabakh conflict—latter stages (circa 1992-1994): includes segments focusing on more general aspects of the conflict, such as its impact on civilians and villages in the region, as well as footage depicting the actual fighting, with the cameraman (Hovhannisyan) embedded with Armenian militias fighting Azerbaijani forces. Time: 7:33:18 Segments: 53-72, 84-105
Post-Soviet Armenia (circa 1992-1994): includes footage of remembrance of the Armenian genocide, foreign aid workers, and footage of everyday life in Yerevan during the fuel blockade, circa winter 1993-1994. Time: 3:26:20 Segments: 80-83, 106-128
Ter-Pétrossian, Lévon, 1945-; Armenia (Republic) |x History |y 1991-; Armenia |x History |x Autonomy and independence movements.; Armenians |z Azerbaijan |z Nagorno-Karabakh.; Earthquakes |z Armenia (Republic); Ethnic conflict |z Azerbaijan |z Nagorno-Karabakh.; Gyumri (Armenia); Kiev (Ukraine); Nagorno-Karabakh (Azerbaijan) |x Ethnic relations.; Nagorno-Karabakh (Azerbaijan) |x History |y 1991-; Nagorno-Karabakh Conflict, 1988-1994; Nationalism |z Former Soviet republics.; Rīga (Latvia); Soviet Union |x History |y 1985-1991; Spitak (Armenia) |x Earthquake, 1988.; Yerevan, Armenia; Yerevan, Armenia |x Politics and government
- Videos
  - Protest on Freedom Square, Yerevan (41:31), circa 1990; ad_barswar1_001_01_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 234 MB (Object 1)
    Contents
    Protest on Freedom Square, in front of Opera House, Yerevan, circa April 1990. series of speakers discussing whether or not youth should be conscripted into the Soviet Army, or into a national army from Armenia. Discussion of the status of Nagorno- Karabakh, and whether it should be united with Armenia or an autonomous region. Also includes footage of protesters camped outside of government building (Parliament?), footage of the wreckage from a plane crash in the mountains, and parishioners lighting candles and a priest officiating at a church service.
  - Public demonstration and funeral, unknown location (41:12), ad_barswar1_001_02_800k_s.mp4ad_barswar1_001_02_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 235 MB (Object 2)
    Flight over mountains, landing at airport in an unidentified city (perhaps Gyumri). Undated. Military forces preparing for a large-scale demonstration. Footage of protest taking place in a public square, with speakers memorializing those fallen in a battle in Shushi, Nagorno-Karabakh. Protest is followed by a funeral procession, with crowd accompanying casket to burial site on a hillside outside city, and graveside service. Time: 41:12
  - Orthodox church service, in remembrance of earthquake victims, Gyumri, part 1 (18:38), circa October 1989; ad_barswar1_002_01_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 106 MB (Object 3)
    Holy Liturgy, Armenian Apostolic Church, at the Yot Verq (Seven Wounds) Cathedral in Gyumri, Armenia, circa October 1989. During the liturgy, the priest expresses condolences for those killed or displaced by the recent earthquake in Northern California, and also remembered those killed in earthquake that hit Armenia and devastated Gyumri the prior year. Also includes footage of damage to buildings in Gyumri from that earthquake. Time: 18:38
  - Orthodox church service, in remembrance of earthquake victims, Gyumri, part 2 (24:25), circa October 1989; ad_barswar1_002_02_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 139 MB (Object 4)
    Holy Liturgy, Armenian Apostolic Church, at the Yot Verq (Seven Wounds) Cathedral in Gyumri, Armenia, continued, circa October 1989. Priest’s homily includes further remarks about the recent earthquake in California, and the earthquake that struck Spitak and Gyumri in December 1988. Priest notes that the leader of the church, His Holiness Karekin I, has sent a letter of condolence and support to President George H.W. Bush of the United States, and a similar letter to the governor of California, George Deukmejian, who is of Armenian descent. Time: 24:25
  - Anti-Soviet protests, unidentified location, Armenia (32:22), ad_barswar1_003_01_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 185 MB (Object 5)
    Anti-Soviet protests, unidentified location in Armenia, and scene in hospital, in which doctors discuss the possible use of poison gas against civilians. Some of the patients in the hospital are victims of this gas attack, and also describe how they were attacked, and doctors speculate about what type of gas had been used. During the protests, civilians argue with members of the militia, who had been stationed at roadblocks guarding several buildings. Members of the crowd taunt soldiers who are thought to be Azeri. Time: 32:22
  - Protest rally, Armenia, with procession to Genocide Memorial in Tsitsernakaberd (40:23), circa 1989-1990; ad_barswar1_004_01_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 231 MB (Object 6)
    Protest event, Freedom Square, Yerevan, circa 1989-1990, includes procession through the streets of Yerevan to the Genocide Memorial at Tstisernakaberd. At the rally, several speakers criticize the Soviet government for having allowed pogroms to be carried out against Armenians in Azerbaijan S.S.R. One speaker, Levon Ter-Petrosyan, the future first president of Armenia, claims that the pogrom in Sumgait could not have happened without the cooperation of government authorities, and holds Soviet leaderMikhail Gorbachev directly responsible. Ter-Petrosyan advocates for the unification of the Armenian majority territories of Nagorno-Karabakh with the rest of Armenia. Time: 40:23
  - Nightime protest rally in Yerevan, and speech by Levon Ter-Petrosyan (01:02:10), ad_barswar1_005_01_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 357 MB (Object 7)
    Protest rally, nighttime, undetermined date, Yerevan. Several speakers address the crowd, including Levon Ter-Petrosyan, who advocates for a general labor strike in Armenia. Other speakers discuss negotiations to resolve the Nagorno-Karabakh crisis, which they claim included delegates from the Soviet central government and the government of Azerbaijan S.S.R., but no Armenian delegates. Discussion of the response of the United States government to these negotiations, as well as the future ofSoviet-led negotiations, are discussed. Time: 1:02:10 ad_barswar1_005_01_800k_s.mp4
  - Protest in Yerevan, and burning of portrait of V.I. Lenin (05:54), circa 1989-=1990; ad_barswar1_005_02_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 34 MB (Object 8)
    Footage of a crowd (during the daytime), blocking a street in Yerevan, possibly Baghramyan Avenue, and burning a portrait of Vladimir Lenin that is attached to a gate, possibly the gate to the parliament building. Time: 05:54
  - Protest rally, nightime, Yerevan (02:19), circa 1989-1990; ad_barswar1_006_01_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 13 MB (Object 9)
    Protest rally, nighttime, presumably Yerevan. The speakers announce that they will provide regular addresses and updates as a means of providing citizens with the most recent news, in an uncensored format. Time: 02:19
  - Protest rally, Freedom Square, Yerevan (10:34), circa 1989-1990; ad_barswar1_007_01_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 61 MB (Object 10)
    Protest rally, Freedom Square, Yerevan, undated. Speakers decry the decision of the government of the Armenian S.S.R. to exclude other parties from negotiations about the fate of Nagorno-Karabakh, and threaten to rise up and take over the country. They also make demands that the Pan-Armenian National Movement be recognized as a party to negotiations. Time: 10:34
  - Protests regarding negotiations concerning the status of Nagorno-Karabakh, Yerevan (47:22), ad_barswar1_007_02_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 270 MB (Object 11)
    Protest, outside of government building, inside of which negotiations are taking place over the fate of Nagorno-Karabakh. Speakers call for governmental reform, the removal of the communist form of government, and the institution of an independent Armenia, which some state is a precondition for the annexation of the territory of Nagorno-Karabakh. Film footage is also included of the negotiations inside of the building, where supporters and opponents of the central (Moscow) government’s role in the negotiations present their cases. Time: 47:22
  - Protest in Yerevan, in front of monument, against policies of Soviet government (47:53), ad_barswar1_008_01_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 273 MB (Object 12)
    Outdoor protest on the steps of a monument in Yerevan (Freedom Square?). Several speakers addressing the crowd praise the Pan-Armenian National Movement, and call of reform, democratization of the government, and freedom of the press. Some in the audience take their Soviet passports and Communist Party membership cards and throw them on the ground, declaring them to be invalid, and claiming that the Armenian government is a puppet of Moscow, and does not represent the Armenian people. Time: 47:53
  - Soldiers, likely Armenian militia, in fog-shrouded valley, unknown location (03:14), ad_barswar1_008_02_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 19 MB (Object 13)
    Soldiers and civilians walk through a valley covered with fog, undated, unidentified location, likely Nagorno-Karabakh. Time: 03:14
  - Public funeral, winter, unknown location (19:44), ad_barswar1_008_03_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 113 MB (Object 14)
    Public funeral of an Armenian named Norayr. Outdoors during winter, snowfall. Speakers call on independence for Armenia, and recall the nation’s history and past greatness. Time: 19:44
  - Memorial to human rights activist Andrei Sakharov, following the announcement of his death (16:06), December 1989; ad_barswar1_009_01_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 92 MB (Object 15)
    Memorial for human rights activist and Soviet dissident Andrei Sakharov, circa December 1989, likely in Yerevan. Event takes place outdoors, on the steps of a public building, at night. Site is festooned with posters, flowers, Armenian flags, as speakers pay their respects to Sakharov. Time: 16:06
  - Protest at the Nairit chemical plant, Yerevan (15:35), circa December 1989; ad_barswar1_010_01_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 89 MB (Object 16)
    Protest of pollution for the Nairit chemical plant, Yerevan, circa 1989-1990. Protesters, some wearing gas masks, march chanting through the streets of Yerevan to the site of the chemical plant, where they continue their protest by setting up Christmas trees and celebrate the traditional new year by singing Armenian folk songs. Time: 15:35
  - Hunger strike protest, at the Tamanyan Monument, Yerevan (03:07), ad_barswar1_011_01_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 18 MB (Object 17)
    Hunger strike in front of the Tamanyan monument, on Tamanyan Street, near the foot of the Cascades, Yerevan. Video shows one man on a hunger strike, sitting at the base of the statue, while others come to visit and speak with him. Time: 03:07
  - Protest near Opera Square, Yerevan, and signing of petitions (03:05), ad_barswar1_011_02_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 17 MB (Object 18)
    Protest near the Opera House, Yerevan, where participants read telegrams and open letters of protest, and sign their names to petitions. Some of the petitions are attached to the entrance of the Yerevan State Medical Institute. Time: 03:05
  - Protest march on Lenin Avenue (Mashtots Avenue), Yerevan (17:12), circa spring 1990; ad_barswar1_011_03_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 96 MB (Object 19)
    Protests on Lenin Avenue (present-day Mashtots Avenue), Yerevan. Large crowds call for the unification of an independent Armenia with Nagorno-Karabakh (referred to as Artsakh). Calls for general strikes and student strikes to begin on 3 May. Time: 17:12
  - Protest rally, Freedom Square, Yerevan (02:28), circa spring 1990 or 1991; ad_barswar1_011_04_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 14 MB (Object 20)
    Protest rally, Freedom Square, Yerevan. Circa spring 1990 or 1991. Speakers criticize the present Armenian government, laud the activities of soldiers, and press for independence of Armenia. Appears to be continued on the next film segment (21). Time: 02:28
  - Protest rally, Freedom Square, Yerevan (07:15), circa spring 1990-1991; ad_barswar1_011_05_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 41 MB (Object 21)
    Protest rally, Freedom Square, Yerevan. Circa spring 1990 or 1991, appears to be continuation of previous recording. Speakers hold up the models of Latvia and Lithuania to follow in drive toward independence for Armenia. The leadership of the Soviet central government, as well as rulers in Georgia and Azerbaijan, are criticized, and the Soviet government is accused of seeking to foment civil war in Armenia by pitting the Pan-Armenian National Movement against other political factions. Time: 07:15
  - Conference of nationalists from various Soviet republics, Kiev, Ukrainian S.S.R. (01:05:51), circa fall 1989; ad_barswar1_012_01_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 374 MB (Object 22)
    Conference, inside auditorium, in Kiev, Ukraine, circa fall 1989. Delegates from various Soviet republics seeking greater autonomy or independence are heard. Representatives from both Azerbaijan and Armenia speak, about the prospects for democracy and reform in their respective lands. Discussion includes the strife in Nagorno-Karabakh. One speaker, Ashot Manucharuyan, representing the Soviet Committee of Nagorno-Karabakh and the Pan-Armenian National Movement, is invited to speak about Armenian aspirations. Footage includes reactions from crowds outside of building, including those supportive of maintaining the Soviet states, as well as some who were prevented from entering the building. Time: 1:05:51
  - March of protesters, Kiev, Ukrainian S.S.R. (44:07), circa fall 1989; ad_barswar1_013_04_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 252 MB (Object 23)
    Protesters, marching through the streets of Kiev, circa fall 1989, carrying Ukrainian flags and chanting slogans, including “Ukraine without Moscow.” In one segment, police try to prevent camera man from filming. Time: 44:07
  - Protests against Soviet Armenian leadership, Yerevan (02:19), circa winter 1990; ad_barswar1_014_01_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 13 MB (Object 24)
    Protesters outside of Armenian parliament, nighttime in winter, with snowfall, circa 1990. Protesters calling for head of Armenian S.S.R. (Suren Harutiunian?) to step down, and for the Nairit chemical plant to be closed. Time: 02:19
  - Hospital scene with wounded men, military checkpoints (05:11), ad_barswar1_015_01_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 29 MB (Object 25)
    Hospital scenes, of two wounded men, one in a surgical unit, winter, unidentified location, likely Nagorno-Karabakh, undated. Also includes footage of travel by car in an unidentified city and its outskirts,showing military checkpoints along the way, and military helicopters. Time: 05:11
  - Expulsion of Armenian residents in Azerbaijan (10:45), circa winter 1990; ad_barswar1_016_01_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 62 MB (Object 26)
    Two scenes, unidentified location or date, possibly Azerbaijan, circa winter 1990: in one, a group of people, seated, are arguing with one another, speaking Russian, about the conditions in Armenia and Azerbaijan, and about Soviet rule. In the second scene, an elderly man is shown dressing to leave his apartment, on Mukhtadira Street, in an unidentified city, after being forced out of it by the authorities. He decries the inability of Armenians and Azerbaijanis to live in peace. He is led, as are others that same evening, into a public building with an Azerbaijani flag at the entrance, which appears to house other elderly people who have been forced out of their homes. Time: 10;45
  - Nationalist protest, Azerbaijan (03:24), ad_barswar1_016_02_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 19 MB (Object 27)
    Crowd of people, mostly men, marching alongside a road in an unidentified location, likely in Azerbaijan. At head of crowd is a man carrying an Azerbaijani flag. Time: 03:24
  - Arrival of flight in Yerevan, with Armenian deportees from Azerbaijan (09:23), circa January 1990; ad_barswar1_016_03_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 54 MB (Object 28)
    Arrival of Armenian deportees, undated, circa January 1990. Footage depicts arrival of Aeroflot jet at night, passengers on the aircraft prior to deplaning, being helped off of aircraft by police and paramedics. Some of the passengers are frail and show signs of bruising and other injuries. Time: 09:23
  - Protesters awaiting word of negotiations between Armenians and representatives of Soviet central government, part 1 (28:04), circa January 1990; ad_barswar1_017_01_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 160 MB (Object 29)
    People marching through streets of Yerevan, undated, circa 14 January 1990. The crowd, many of whom raise clenched fists, proceed toward the parliament building,where they wait outside, to hear news of the outcome of negotiations between representatives of Armenia and the Soviet government. At various points, officials and members of the political opposition come out to the courtyard to address the crowds. Time: 28:04
  - Protesters awaiting word of negotiations between Armenians and representatives of Soviet central government, part 2 (23:47), circa January 1990; ad_barswar1_017_02_800k_s.mp4; 1.0 Video recording 136 MB (Object 30)
    Appears to be continuation of previous tape, on evening of same day. In this footage, protesters are speaking in the square in front of the parliament building in Yerevan. As an Armenian leaders and Soviet officials come out to address the crowd, the latter beginchanting “Artsakh” (Armenian name for Nagorno-Karabakh). A Soviet official addresses the crowd, summarizing the points that were addressed during the discussions earlier that day. Armenian speakers call for independence for Nagorno-Karabakh, and weapons for Armenian forces, since they feel that Soviet forces will not defend them. Time: 23:47
  - Public funerals of Armenian militia fighters (32:47), 1.0 Video recording 33 MB (Object 31)